of in the final and there will be
representatives from the USA Germany
Ukraine and Canada Great Britain Spain
Australia and Malaysia and of course -
from Chinese as well in the competition
tonight it's gonna be a thrilling one
certainly if the previous two rounds are
anything to go by and then crown are
delighted after the introduction of
Xavier Garcia C rather unexpectedly
Chris Meers has made a throw to a final
preliminary she was the best they could
manage at the World Championships in
Shanghai last year this time round he's
gone to better and made it into the top
12 this man is very used to being in the
top 12
twice silver medalist at the Olympics in
this very event
Alexander Tea Party of Canada Ilya
Kumasi of Ukraine and will certainly be
in the mix as will this man all the
remaining divers being introduced will
be competing for probably a bronze maybe
a silver we have maybe a fly in the
ointment for the Chinese coming up in
just a moment we'll introduce him after
troy Dumais has been introduced to the
crowd there's a few divers who have been
diving exceptionally well and
consistently well - and here's one of
them the r Castillo who went up second
ranked of the Chinese after the semi
files is Qin Kai and it just missed out
on the medal at the World Championships
last year in fourth place but here's the
almost unknown quantity though we do
know what he can do silver medalist of
the world championship last year
separating out the Chinese Ilya Zakharov
but the red-hot favorite surely is the
world champion
Olympic champion no Xiang ready to do
battle once again with the eleven of the
divers it could be a very interesting
hour and a half or so very unpredictable
the first two rounds have been no reason
suspect that tonight may not be in a
similar vein alongside me the 2004
synchro ten meter silver medalist Leon
Taylor well we haven't been disappointed
so far and I think the state to get me
knocked up just a a bit I'll sue tonight
well this is what all the divers have
been aiming to do you've got to make it
through the preliminaries you've got to
make it through these semi finals and
this is where the work starts none of
the points carry through each of the
divers will be performing six dives the
most difficult dives humanly possible
they'll be going in different directions
there are five groups of dive there's
the forward the backwards there's also
the inward which is where you stand
backwards on your tiptoes but you jump
away from the diving board and spin
forward
there's the reverse which is where you
walk down the diving board jumping away
from it but spin backwards towards it
there's also the twist where you move
look at twisting longitude early as well
as fitting in somersaults and then you
get one dive that you can choose any one
of those five groups so what you're
gonna see today is well if their
freedoms and semi-finals are anything to
go by it's gonna be extraordinary as you
deal with those headphones on that
little baby they're almost as big as the
kid's head on to the judges these are
the ones who will have the destiny and
the outcome of the mainstream it's a
springboard in their hands would you
like me to explain the judging before we
kick off Bobby the judges explained
judging I can't explain the judges but I
will explain how the judging works in in
all individual contests so there are
seven execution judges who mark the
diver out of ten the two highest and two
lowest marks are then crossed off and
you will see those appear on your screen
with lines through them to leave three
roars those are then totaled multiplied
by the Associated degree of difficulty
to give the total
for that give and die or six totals are
added together to give the overall
placings right now we've marked your
card on how it works and what's likely
to happen in the next hour and a half
let's get on with the action and start
with the first round first round of six
remember five in the women's competition
six in the men's and just sneaking in
and they very final qualifying place
number 12 here's Ken yo 12 years he will
quit after these games only made the
preliminaries in Sydney in 2000 his
opening dive for three and a half summer
sorts with Pike oh if that's a sign of
what is to come we are in for a real
treat
Kenny yo starting with his forward three
and a half perfectly on the end of the
diving board squeezing into that Pike
shape slipping into the water without
very much splash that's a big opening
man died for him 88.5 incoming and a big
total score to start off his campaign in
this Olympic final for him seventy nine
point zero five Kenya now on to ethan
warren from australia only one
australian and she entered in this event
but he's made it through to the final
and he will go with a back two and a
half summer sorts with pike this time
not 3.1 but 3.0 degree of difficulty
which of course will be what the marks
he gets will be x oh it's pretty good
it's straight up and down he is well
that died was throwing up a little bit
too much splash for more than an eighth
which is a shame the aerial work is good
backwards there's the pike shape comes
out in plenty of time enters the water
it's good it'll get eights I'm short but
it needs to be clean him into the water
check out this super slow-mo shot here
as he exits the dive putting his chin
back to look at the water reaches back
it's pretty good just too much
yep happy enough it would seem with that
maybe a brave face on it but 72 is the
opening score for Ethan Warren 20
year-old from Australia goes into second
place for the time being
Xavier Garcia of Spain training in
Canada these days seventh in Rome 2009
and Nathan Shanghai a year ago now it's
really coming in to form these past few
years decided to train overseas and he's
certainly been working hard he's in
great shape he used to be a little
heavier than that but he's obviously
working with a fantastic team in Canada
teammate of Alexander de Partie or he'll
be up soon that could squeeze eight from
the judges he's clean him into the water
than Ethan before him again 3.0 dd
couple of eights and 7.5 to give him a
total when you 7.50
this man's have a great couple of days
well the boy became a man right before
the eyes of the Aquatic Centre in London
Britain's Chris Meers his opening dive
easier once he'll do it's all relative
of course 3.0 degree of difficulty
starting dive he looks pretty steady
again and the crowd of enjoying that
ripping the roof off there's his mum and
dad and the rest of his family holding
up the tents that's only gonna get ate
but there we go smiling before he sets
off you've got to use this crowd you
can't block it Ike you've got a smile
rise to the occasion exactly what he did
in the semi-finals and that's a lovely
star it'll get over 70 points it's good
enough yeah it's alright 72 is what we
anticipate 72 is
we get we're 3/8 multiply the course by
the degree of difficulty giving you 72
and that's not tip nicely into equal
second at the moment Alexander de Partie
again it's a three point zero it's the
back at two and a half in the pike
position yeah
silver medalist four years ago silver
medalist back in 2004 fourth Olympic
Games truly exceptional athlete been
through the middle in the build-up to
this one plenty of injuries we're talk
more about that later that's not the
start that Alex would be looking for
just tipping over a vertical as he
enters the water that may be trying a
little bit too hard technically so
proficient such an elegant diver just a
shame they're a little bit off I wonder
whether he can bounce back well it's
racing your way as ever proposes
thoughts get himself ready for round two
72 is the score for de Partie which
matches Mears and Warren in round one
Illya Vasa with all that tape on his
back you know when we get a moment we'll
explain exactly what's holding him
together
is it superglue 3.24 is his opening
gambit in with three and a half summer
sorts with tuck so a big degree of
difficulty to start with oh it always
makes the crowds take a little bit of an
intake of air because the inward
movement is the one where you are
relatively close to the diving board
standing backwards spinning forward
kibosh is actually for me a little bit
too tight to the diving board and he
seemed going by he does a good job on at
Lee and his three point four degree of
difficulty so it will score a relatively
good total points but the execution he's
tipping over a vertical there as he goes
in yeah a little bit too close to the
board for me the tape will hold him
together that's his lower back injury
has
more or less matching what he did in the
semi-finals seventy eight point two zero
for kavaja will lift him because that
higher degree of difficulty into second
place
Patrick housing of Germany not quite so
ambitious with his opening dive is a 3.0
and you've seen it before it's that back
two and a half summer sorts with hike
oh what a dive that is the best executed
dive we've seen so far in this
competition we are in the early stages
but what you're looking for here is
great elevation from the diving board
beautiful Pike shape and he absolutely
cruises it slipping into the water with
absolutely no splash eight point five s
I think it's worth a nine let's see what
the judges think well for once the
judges to sakru de Leon Taylor they're
not gonna have any of that eight point
five it is across the board near the
marks the count seven six point five
zero only one American remains in the
lineup problems just cool earlier in the
competition this is Troy do mate three
point one open for him forward three and
a half somersaults in the position oh
look at that entry well sometimes
thinking that no one actually went in
there is not enough splash to fill a tea
cup because I've heard said many times
before Troy to may is certainly on fire
bonds medalist already this is going to
get nines well definitely should get
nine should be all over it look at that
precision almost perfection just a
little bit low on the water needs to be
a little bit higher in my opinion for
nine point five so maybe Anil even the
elusive ten throwing down the proverbial
gauntlet isn't it lines across the board
eighty three point seven zero with that
degree of difficulty now it's do Mexico
forward two and a half seven sorts to
twist three point four degree of
difficulty
or the cried like that because there's a
lot going on so that's the forward two
and a half with two twists you'll see a
lot of the athletes using this yell game
of tactics coming out with his big guns
three point four here we are here's one
and a half somersault so actually one
then he comes out double twist he's a
little bit stuck there so he does get it
in it lands on his head
it'll get eights and eight point five
look at the expression on his face as he
goes into the double twist he's been on
fire yesterday and today and he
continues to like the blue touch paper
yeah he's been the early leader on both
occasions both in the preliminaries and
now 70 files and could well be the
leader of the first round here with that
eighty six point seven zero on to the
first of the two Chinese this is the one
that missed out on a medal at the World
Championships in Shanghai last summer
yes
King Kai's back two and a half
somersaults 3.0 you've seen it before
comes again that's more like it punching
kite back two and a half opting to open
with this easiest dive now some of the
divers aren't so it gives an unfair look
at the scoreboard because that's a
beautiful dive just saving as he goes
into bending at the hips actually
arching of the lower back and bending at
the knees to try and stop the dive from
going over a vertical which he does a
very very good job on if he gets 80
points on this it's a job well done
80 and more 81 points of Ching Kai
we're three nines counting towards our
total we see one diver
go above a hundred marks this is he
India's Acker off it came in the final
round of the semi final this morning so
expensive early on birds well three
point eight it's a three point four in
with three and a half seven sort with
tuck
or he means business this afternoon he
was a bit shaky in the semi-final he was
top qualifier for the semi-final now has
a demeanor of the great Dmitri sighting
canny emulate him can he win Olympic
gold today if he continues to dive like
this he'll certainly be in contention
88.5 incoming for this amazing dive
three point for putting the pressure on
the Olympic champion who's up next
six points better than the most in the
semi files earlier today's a crop 85
just buying Castillo Puerta just ahead
are Troy do Mei Chong world champion
Olympic champion three World Series wins
this year in Moscow Beijing and Dubai
again dive its favored by many of
finalists is that back two and a half
somersault again Pike position 3.0 oh
it's not as good as you would expect
from the Olympic champion you can see
his teammates they're just giving him
polite applause rather than standing up
and whooping and hollering the aerial
work is exceptional is way above the
five meter he's super flash putting his
feet right down at the water cruising
round but he goes over a vertical I
don't think that's worth more than seven
point five eight maybe and he chung is
off the pace competition on 8.0
right across the board times the degree
of difficulty will put him in the top
eight that's how things look after the
first round of dives a long way to go
yet five more rounds remember Castillo
wet again leading the way early stages
Sakharov Dumais Ching Kai
a commercial last name on that screen
then de Partie nochang and Chris Meers
all with the same score as has Ethan
Warren and slightly tailed off but not
too much as Xavier Garcia after round
number one aren't around to front of a
expectant crowd a very noisy crowd a
very enthused crowd who won't see the
best diving and that's exactly what
they're going to do in this Olympic
final of the 3-meter springboard in the
yo its first ever final at the Olympics
two twists no he's done okay his takeoff
just letting him down a little bit
capturing all the footage to coach his
using the tablets there to instantly
capture the dive just a little bit back
from the end of the diving board so when
he comes out into his double twist here
he's falling a little bit too quickly
and so it runs out of room a little bit
it's still good I'm sure it'll go over
75 7008 which is a good dive but Wow
you know this is the Olympic final
seventy eight point two zero and good
see the coaches reading the instructions
take tablets with water very good on to
the Australian Ethan Warren equal eight
after the first bit of pro doesn't mean
an awful lot at this stage for three and
a half seven sorts with Pike's slightly
moving up in terms of degree of
difficulty three point one this time so
three point zero well it's pretty good
end of the dive short of vertical
there's Matthew Mitchum Olympic champion
from Australia on the platform whistling
and cheering he's 20 year old teammate
on it's a fantastic job to get this
fight just comes out the time a little
bit early they're leaving it short as he
entered the water so he won't go over 70
points on that and that'll leave him off
the pace already at these early stages
but I didn't expect him to be in the top
six there we go that's fresh and says it
or doesn't it I love it because you know
exactly what he thinks about dive
he doesn't hide his expressions or his
emotions even those thumbs up in a smile
to follow but I think the initial
expression told you what you need to
know
Xavier Garcia for two and a half two
twists oh that's a really really good
dive now I'm not sure what the judges
are going to make of it he did move
towards us here in the commentary box
quite a lot which gives the impression
that the dive is dare I say skew if here
we go he's spinning towards us loses her
legs a little bit the entry into the
water is superb but you can see he's
moving towards us now if the judges spot
that they might penalize him if they
don't spot it he's going to get a big
big score here he comes
lovely entry into the water which the
judges have spotted today's body is
going a little bit erroneous halfway
through
no thanks point seven zero takes him
into second place now the huge roar you
heard not surprisingly to greet the
arrival of Great Britain's crispy is
second round dive reverse two and a half
somersaults he's just let the tide go
over he's obviously pumped full of
adrenaline you see those coach on the
Left Lindsey Fraser
he knows you get instant feedback yes
toes over the end he was hanging ten so
he did well to wait then he thought he
was spinning slower than he was but he's
way up in the air over a vertical a
little bit of a timber that's actually a
bit of a blown dive there for Chris such
a shame he did all the hard work yeah it
dropped a few too many points they were
afraid
not comparable with what he did earlier
today 58.50 for Chris Meers now I'll put
him at the bottom of the pack of those
who have gone that so far Alexandre de
Partie reversed two and a half
somersaults one and a half twists in the
pike position 3.30 it's done really well
way back from the end of the diving
board such a shame because if alex is on
the end of the diving board this dive is
all his but that it could see him
shaking his head as he gets like because
it's so difficult you've got a jump you
know forwards and then spin backwards
towards it one and a half twist two and
a half somersault it might squeeze eight
but I would expect to see 9s from Alex
if he wants to stay in the hunt for that
third Olympic medal on the banks in this
event gonna be tough out there for him
today
well a couple of judges quite liked it
one judge will get the line through
eight point five will count towards the
total of 80 points
eighty-five Alexandre de Partie now
Anika vasha some problems it's a big in
its forward four and a half somersaults
with tuck 3.8 into the big Terrace early
or you can say you can say well I think
that might have been your fault Bob
you said it could causing some problems
and right on cue the problem started the
take-off on this is so so important he's
on the corner of the diving board means
he can't push down with confidence for
he's lacking height lacking rotation and
running out of room he needed a 3.5
meter springboard see him invite on the
corner left-hand corner of the board Wow
kibosh off the pace as well yeah that's
his big dive blown I'm afraid in terms
of spread on the marks they're 4.5 up to
6 they saw it slightly differently for a
judging perspective the marks aren't
overly impressive for a high tariff dive
sixty eight point four zero on to the
remaining German Patrick housing for
three and a half three point one with
technically exceptionally good maybe a
little bit of a turn as he went into the
water there I don't know but the judges
will spot that let's have a look
spotting the water spotting the water
there he goes it comes in yes I can see
both feet slightly there it shows me an
over twist but I think the judges might
not see that or they tend to be letting
those go a little bit still there's a
very good dive looking over to the coach
for instant feedback was that okay
your might little bit over yeah I can
feel going over just a touch there you
go
is there an argument having judges
straight on as well as on the side as
well so he could get a vision of that or
a view of that no the judges always been
from the side it's kind of keep that
stability okay
Troy doom a reverse two and a half
somersaults one half twist three point
three in the pike position
well not quite as clean into the water
as his first round dive but not far away
at all yeah Steve Foley their high
performance director for USA moved away
from the UK and has been working out
there and look at this multiple medals
for USA diving in Troy to may is
certainly in contention so far that's a
big opening dive backed up straight away
with a very good second-round reverse
one off just in to and off 84 yeah
improvement on this morning as well as
indeed both dives have been he's
definitely in the credit column with an
84 point one five for Troy Dumais now
welter of Mexico getting into the reason
behind three point eight most of those
come late on in the other programs in
with three and a half somersaults with
tuck 3.44 Castillo who was the current
leader Oh sounded like it was a women's
tennis match there a little bit of
grunting and groaning but it seemed to
work for him swing in his arms
depressing the diving board being
patient waiting for the diving board to
throw him back up up up and away
he's only very short when he gets in
that shape he spins around like a
dingbat
if you think about spins around anyway
he goes zipping into the water with
hardly any splash and that's her eighty
point 85 dawn yeah I don't think David
that wasn't any danger quite frankly
last comment 85 from Castillo Wednesday
and it keeps him in the first place
Qin Kai our China forward two and a half
somersaults two twists Pike position
three point four on the degree of
difficulty or steady unfaltering an
unwavering so far we see Ching Kai
wobbling around a little bit in the
premiums in the semi as he seems pretty
steady so far a little bit corner board
there and he comes out forward two and
half two twists it's three point four
needed to be good and that's certainly
good really be catching up with the
Mexicans lead I think you'd be closing
it just marginally still a way to go yet
yeah he is closing but it hasn't quite
reached it yet and they're still
slightly behind Troy do me but only by
0.15 of a point and that puts the
Chinese the first of the two Chinese
into third place in Lea's zakharov
second after the first round he's got a
big dive to finish off the program with
this one not quite so big with picking
our 3.50 on and nailed it this is
actually very impressive because he's
the only diver actually up in the ante
the backward group of dyes all of the
others in this final are doing a back
two and a half in the pike position
playing safe with a 3-0 zakharov is
going all guns blazing this is three
point five degree of difficulty and he's
absolutely drilled it this is going to
sail over 80 points the Gamble has paid
off and the pressure lands firmly on the
next divers shoulders now remember we
haven't seen any tens that count yet I
think we might well do in the final yeah
91 that's decisive that is a decisive
die from zakharov 38.5 x the degree of
difficulty that's how you arrive with
that figure it's actually 13 points
higher than need to get and
today that's massive now her Chong has
responded oh he doesn't respond but not
in the way that he would have liked to
I'm not sure what the taping on the
fingers is those of you that are asking
it's peculiar normally see it on the
toes because the board's quite abrasive
now he Chong here really given it some
beans look at him way above the sitter
5-meter almost as high as a 7.5 million
but he goes over he over cooks it if you
will look at him can't even stop it's so
easy for him to adjust his soup but he
went in there which shows he was going
over a rotation all 8 it's good but it's
not good enough to take the lead
well he only puts him in 7th place with
someone from where he was good but
there's a man of the moment and the man
at the top of the standings Ilya
Zakharov from Russia has a bout a 5
point lead well they're about over young
Castillo went up there troy do mate
Ching Kai and yo good start from him and
Xavier Garcia has moved off the bottom
in the 6th and here come the remaining
divers Chris Meers about 10 points
adrift of Ethan Warren in 12th place
look at her chong world champion in
seventh after two rounds defending
Olympic champion as well of course so he
knows what it's like to stand on that
podium to win a gold at the Olympic
Games but Sakharov he's your man at the
moment and believe you me he's got some
big big dives to come will they catch
him exciting stuff as we head into round
3 six rounds in total so this will
represent halfway my time all 12 divers
have gone and yo in fifth place after
round 2 reversed two and a half with
pike dive go over as he went in just I
think he might have felt a little bit
tight to the diving board so he stayed
in his Pike shape a fraction too long he
go he's not too far away from the diving
board so yeah as he reaches back all
over there he comes to splash going back
towards the diving board not quite time
to get your surfboards out but nearly
yeah mistimed entry spotted of course by
the judges and e- 5.5 is where he gets
across the board so less than fifty
forty nine point five zero in a very
good start has come to a rather abrupt
end now we're into the three point eight
again ether more on going for an in
round three forward four-and-a-half
seller sorts with tuck big degree of
difficulty
obviously assigned to that a big risk it
comes off looks great oh it does to the
Gamble's paying off there's his
teammates on their feet the coaches are
even impressed that must mean it's good
three point eight this is his biggest
degree of difficulty almost on the end
of the diving board waits patiently
throws in and close himself up in the
air just spotting the water as he goes
in that's great will it get over 90
points
that's the question three point eight to
create difficulties so impressed with
these divers twenty years old from
Australia weekend the scores
yeah ninety one point two zero high
score in the competition so far for
Ethan Warren that leaps him up he's in
11th place can he ranked one after that
yes
yeah just showing you how difficult that
dive is he wasn't waiting around for Bob
to introduce him so where he goes
looking to get the dive out the way
going for broke he didn't use this in
the semi-finals here he is this is his
big dive doesn't quite get into the tuck
shape well enough a little bit loose and
so when he comes out he drops like a
stone yeah what a shame there what an
absolute shame into the hot tub to keep
warm
he knows he's Olympic quest for a medal
is over yeah trigger the head hands on
hips
all the body language tells you when he
knows he's just now playing for a decent
spot at the end Chris Meers lapping up
the adulation going for the reverse two
and a half somersaults one half twists
as the first of the upping the ante
dives from Chris Meers after the two
threes he's a three point three boy he
had it on the take-off just playing a
little bit safe as he went into the
water he sailed over on his sacrament
ivory now he's just a little bit short
on his third round look pretty good on
the end of the timing board one and a
half twist into the two and a half
somersaults all looks good he just stops
it a little bit short what a shame the
splash being thrown away from the diving
board a little bit too much of it seven
and a half's I think not quite as good
as earlier a little bit behind the able
there's some great expressions they were
there 7.5 across the border Chris Meers
times the degree of difficulty 3.3 gives
you 70 4.25 Alex Day parties reverse two
and a half with Pike that's more like it
now are we going to see the first
perfect ten that isn't very far away
that's nine point five it's very very
good it needed to be Alex opting for a
slight still doesn't look happy come on
Alex give us a smile nine point five I'm
predicting that's an absolutely stunning
reverse two and a half squeezing into
that Pike shape looking where he's been
rather than where he's going points his
toes towards the scoreboard and buries
the entry judges maybe being a little
mean on that nines across the board
eighty-one good mark
very good mark but could have been
should have been perhaps a little bit
better than that it was day party into
first place for the time being in the
kibosh is reversed two and a half on our
twists
well that's good from kibosh it just
rolling over on his entry into the water
just marginally the tape on the back
obviously to support that area divers
get a lot of problems they are bending
and moving themselves in such a
ballistic and dynamic way
lots of aches and pains and injuries
occur training for long long hours ok
Russia being held together by sticky
tape literally anyway he's made it
through the prelims of Sammy's and
hippies in the final and that's one of
his brother dives we have a technology
we will rebuild him and they have
seventy nine point two zero for kavaja
and up to third he goes Patrick housing
now eightth in Beijing the worlds in
Shanghai last year three point nine this
one oh it's worth shouting and screaming
about house thing coming out all guns
blazing moving himself up on the
semi-final way who's doing this dive
with two twists busting out the big one
now with the forward two and a half with
three twists one two three he must be
dizzy by the time he finishes that many
twists he does a good job to get in that
degree of difficulty is huge the
execution is probably seven seven point
five but on a three point nine that's
going to get you 85 points plus house
ding Wow incredible Wow indeed he's
wowed the crowd and the judges with that
eighty-seven point seven five and
housing with that go for broke dive
really has moved up into first place
just ahead
Alexander Day party now here's another
man who's on the forum tonight he's
first two dives number three coming up
now at roy doom a it's the easy one
compared to the earlier ones hey back
two and a half several sorts with Mike
at only 3.0 degree of difficulty you
know this is the dive the weakest I've
enjoyed amazed list he used to open with
it but he used to to leave him with too
much to do anyway he's decided to move
it to the middle of his program and it
seems to be working much better there
it's obviously still only 3.0 degree of
difficulty but if he's scoring more than
eight which he will on that then that's
a really good effort might move him down
the leaderboard not because he didn't
perform it well enough
because of its low degree of difficulty
we've seen some big dives going in and
some big dive still to come
well he's still hanging on in there he's
in the first place for the time being
with that seventy six point five zero
and it's getting a bit bunched at the
top something with dumain housing not
much between them and here is the second
ranked diver after round to Mexico for
four and a half years Oh cast Elios on
the money
this is his bogey dive forward four and
a half three point eight degree of
difficulty and this one's so easy to
make a mistake on his back from the end
a little bit a couple of inches away but
he up up and away he's so small so
compact that when he gets into that
shape he just spins and spins this is
gonna be big it's gonna go over 90
points so it should - and Castillo
Mexico on fire what a competition this
is turning into 95 for Kayla Castillo
welt up
he now has would you believe a 22 point
lead over du made a sizable at this
stage of the competition ching hai's
reversed three and a half seven sorts
the chinese not quite yet oh that's
decisive bob was laying it down they're
not quite in the groove and that he's
just slipped right into his groove my
goodness here we go
reverse three and a half somersaults
spinning backwards towards the diving
board it's very easy to get
disorientated and he's absolutely buried
the entry hardly any splash 99.5 s just
showing you the strain on the divers
body Wow beautiful dive are we getting
some marks in this round a walk Ethan
Warren's 91 95 from Castillo Huerta and
now ninety six point two five from Ching
Kai and he goes into second place but
not a million miles behind Castillo
quarter here zakharov what do you have
analyst reversed three and a half some
sort with tuck
oh it's almost as good as ching hai's
almost as good he's up higher than ching
hai's in fact I actually like to dive
more
however he just moves on the entry just
tips over vertical ever so slightly he's
gonna get eight and a half he might get
eight eight eight and a half it's not
quite worth nines
oh it's ninety points though well there
are there abouts he's responding staying
in contention
yeah the marks it will count our eight
point five times that degree of
difficulty you get eighty nine point two
five boy is this competition hotting up
hardly anything separating the top three
and will be on top four after we've seen
her Cheong surely reverse three and a
half several sorts with tuck three point
five just taking his time as he
contemplates a very big dive oh it's
gonna be there well there abouts on
eight and a half isn't that interesting
chink I Ilya Zakharov and he Chong all
of which like for like the reverse three
and a half Ching Kyle ain't Anna's
marker and I think he won that round
he Chong doing a great job they're just
tipping over a vertical like sacrify
think you'll pretty much get the same
marks as zakharov what does that do to
the scoreboard who is in the lead
halfway through this exciting contest
well it is not what we anticipated and
saying her Chong not what he anticipated
cuz he ought surely me think he's infra
metal probably in the big G big G
alluding him now look at this after
round three yella Castilla welter Ilya
Zakharov chin Kai Troy do Mei is about
19 points adrift her Chong has a lot of
ground to make up there after counting
in six behind of course the top three
don't falter they party on page two and
Chris Meers bringing up the rear but
closing in on Kenny Oh in 11th place
this is a competition and we haven't
seen the best of it yet
the defending Olympic champion removing
himself on the hot tub going back to his
spot wherever he's sitting to compose
himself halfway through the competition
he's got some work to do and at the
moment is not in a medal place maybe not
in a very good place either round four
can yo are Malaysia starting things off
for the reverse two and a half
somersaults 1/2 twists Pike oh he's back
into it with a sparkly one that's a good
dive fair from Kelly Oh poured that poor
third round dive for find dive he's got
himself back up for it that's a great
dive three point three to create
difficulty this okay eights and eight
point five s it's a very good dive but
you can't afford to make any mistakes no
damage done in round three forty nine
point five zero which is not anywhere
near what do you require but seventy
nine point two zero is good reaction and
a good comeback by Kenny Oh Ethan
warrant eight after round three in with
three and a half seven spots were tucked
three point four for the Australian
Mike's give us his immediate impressions
all his diver Susi leaves the diving pit
let's see what he could do in round four
you're he's backed it up his third round
I've four forward four and half sailed
over 90 points this is slightly lower
degree of difficulty but I'd say this is
going to get mid-80s beautiful dive
waits patiently goes into the water with
hardly a ripple of splash you know what
you're looking for now and the judges
certainly know what they're looking for
and it's something along those lines
good work I'm over a smile and thumbs up
thank you eighty six point seven zero
before Ethan Warren didn't let me down
and doesn't let himself down or
Australia down for that matter and
they're creeps into first place
Xavier Garcia with the reverse three and
a half with tuck no he's going for Polk
and I think his campaign is broken now
unfortunately Ford four and a half
previously shorter vertical yet raised
eyebrows from the coaches and this one
the surf is definitely up here we go
reverse three and a half just hangs on
into his touch shape a little bit too
long and over he goes and here comes the
wave get your surfboard type 42 not my
age sadly three fours
where's Mia's
came through the preliminaries in the
final position moved up a couple of
places run a few places actually to make
that final and now finds himself in the
final in round four with a Ford two and
a half seven sorts two twists so again
just to not jump on the degree of
difficulty this is a three point four
performed in the pike position oh it's
good funk Chris I'm actually taken aback
by the noise that this pride generates
it is quite extraordinary yeah
he's holding his composure making a
slight arrow on his previous round I've
that's good it's a little bit short as
he goes in he does disguise it very well
maybe you're sneaking a tour to fajn the
judges it's straight up and down it is
3.4 degree of difficulty could get close
to 80 points these are the max the count
eight 7.5 7.5 78 points to zero for
Chris Meers quite as aware of the camera
as Ethan is Alexander Day party for
seventh after three in with three and a
half somersaults with tuck three point
four a degree of difficulty it's a good
dive you can hear the cheers from the
coaches who were just behind the judges
he is a little bit over a vertical but
it's worth saying six weeks ago
Alexander de Partie hit the diving board
with his head on this dive he has 22
stitches or had 22 stitches on his
forehead and is just showing the courage
and the strength of character in this
young man silver medals - in this event
in Athens and Beijing and he's here
today to hang on to that Olympic dream I
read somewhere the cut was ten point
five centimeters long eighty three point
three zero for de Partie who departs now
to Ilya kvasir the three point five
reverse three and a half somersaults
you can only finds himself in night then
probably not challenging for a medal on
this occasion boys aerial work is very
very good just fractionally over as he
went into the water it's a big dive and
well everyone's doing big dives this is
so impressive what it is the Olympic
final after all wow just consistently
very good to get himself through look at
the strain and power watching the knees
come in spinning around so quickly pops
his feet up reaches back just tipping
over beat there's a good job saving it
and you get over 80 points for that
eighty two point two five remember all
those marks with a line through do not
count towards the total the ones without
do times the degree of difficulty
Patrick housing in with three and a half
several sorts with tuck takes place
after round three but it's very tight
for the bronze medal position at the
moment boys yes didn't quite get out of
the dive quickly enough as he went into
water he's very tall as a diver so he
doesn't have to work a little bit harder
to fit in all these rotations and
technically he is absolutely spot-on
just a little bit low on the water here
you see him just straightening out as
he's entering so I think he's only
giving you at 7s 7.5 s and that will put
him slightly off the pace yep we've the
confirmation on scoreboard lowest score
joint lowest score he's had so five four
rounds and they're talking it over with
a coach smile to follow because he knows
precisely what he has done
not a bad dive not quite what he hoped
for 70 6.50
troy Dumais can he be adding to the US
medal tally in the Aquatic Centre this
week both swimming of course very
proficient and prolific and diving doing
pretty well two inward three and a half
somersaults with tuck for do maze fourth
round dive degree of difficulty three
point four on this
oh it's a decisive dive for domain he
just fluffed it ever so slightly as he
went in just ever so slightly is always
low on the water he's not as strong as
the other athletes here we go
technically is over the diving board a
safe distance away you could just see
here a little bit short as he goes in
loses his feet throwing up a little bit
of splash now will the judges penalize
him heavily
or will he sneak over 80 points if he
does thank good on him his family
cheering whooping and hollering as
always there's six and a half for one
judge eight from the others interesting
very interesting as somebody once said
81.6 zero troy do mate oldest competitor
in the competition at 32 years of age
now this could be a pivotal dive a young
El Castillo quarter oh the Mexicans are
on fire this well I'm not surprised
they're punch in the air so am I yo
castelia I thought he'd used up all his
good dives in the prelims and Semien I'm
pleased to say he's proving me wrong
he's worked so hard his consistency is
squashed so so good this is a decisive
dive it's the one that he could have
wobbled on and he's absolutely drilled
it is hit 90 points it's gonna be close
- it's almost there eighty six point
seven first round 85 second round 95
third round and fourth round dive eighty
nine point two five gives him a 30 point
lead over Troy Dumais at this stage Wow
chin Kai in with three and a half summer
sorts with tuck has a lot of pressure on
the Chinese here this is not going quite
as we'd anticipated this is three point
four there
ah Ching Kai eating up the pressure I
don't even know whether he knows it's in
the arena
unfazed an unfaltering inward right over
the diving board squeezing into the Tuck
shape cruising piking out of it showing
the judges how easy it is for him this
is going to be 90 points as well look at
the strength in those legs absolutely
precise Wow I think that's what we call
game on now yeah 91 point eight zero one
and two separated by point two zero of a
mark
I like zakharov like it more to the
point for two and a half seven shots to
twist is he gonna put himself back in
pole position after this oh yes I think
you will three point for the same degree
of difficulty that we've just seen from
Ching Kai and this is the easiest of his
last three dives and this is by no means
easy look how he just cruise his double
twist so much time if anything he's just
a little bit too far away from the
diving board four nines should get eight
point five let's see the judges might
penalize because he is in the middle of
the pool should have swam to the far end
got a time for us eighty six point seven
zero in third but I know it's not a cast
adrift third by any means at three point
three points behind silver exactly four
points behind the leader who is still a
Castillo went up on the way her Chong
fifth the world champion Olympic
champion and a little bit of pressure
here three point four in with three and
a half somersault with tuck
boy he hasn't responded he is a little
bit off his game it just goes to show
what the occasion could do to people he
is feeling the occasion the defending
champion is slightly off his game and
you cannot be slightly off your game he
is by no means out of it so he Chong is
still very much in the hunt for medals
but he's certainly not way out in front
where he's accustomed to being just
tipping over a vertical it's gonna get
eights and 8.5 but he would he needed
nine to 9.5 to keep up with the pack
well I'm very intrigued is he got 85 he
has to make up 28 points to get gold
right now 28 points is he gonna do that
no unlikely unless people make mistakes
he could end up at the medals and that
would be a shock here's how it looks
after round four this is thrilling it's
very entertaining and we're on the edges
of our seats hope you are too look at
that hardly four points exactly four
points that you bother you using your
fingers and toes between one and three
champion struggling for medals Chris
Meers off the bottom into 11th place
ground just seen that on the scoreboard
and he finished above 12th well I was
happy to be in the final of course but
any progress you can make up that
leaderboard he'll be delighted with
that's what it is
that's where we are London 2012 which
has been a roaring success every
departments and it has been for the
Chinese who won an free gold medal in
diving so far but at the moment they're
not start of the penultimate round of
the men's 3-meter springboard final it
is wide open for the medals and it's not
being dominated by the Chinese at this
stage Ken yo with his Panama dive in
with three and a half summer sorts with
tuckworth three point four on the degree
of difficulty
yeah it's one of Ken's trickier dives
his biggest degree of difficulty at
three point four and he's done a very
good job with it
come in turn off that extraordinary high
at the end of the last one there we're
seeing the big guns going at each other
Ken bringing us down to some kind of
reality but that is a very well executed
dive lots of people asking about the
cloth that divers seem to use it's
actually called a chamois Sammy Lee who
invented the Sam he's actually here he
competed in the 1948 Olympic Games stick
tie off the divers in between drives
keep them warm so their muscles don't
get too cold but also to dry their hands
and shin so they can hold on to those
shapes hope that makes sense at home
that's where Sammy the show-me came from
exactly okay seventy six point five zero
for cameo with his fifth round dive the
second up is Ethan Warren on Australia
who's not out of it yet you know he's
sixth place with very good dives
here comes the reverse three and a half
why leaks it in as well with hardly a
ripple of splash very good he's
certainly upped his game he's a bit here
and there in the prelims and made it
through all lands used to stop himself
falling back in the pool Wow he
certainly didn't fall in the pool on
this one just 20 years old from
Australia first saw him a couple of
years ago and the Commonwealth Games in
Delhi and I was ultra impressed now and
he isn't failing to deliver here in this
final Wow exceptional diving eighty nine
point two five now he's going for a bit
of a run as well conserve your energy
boy these guys are ultra fit don't look
at me when you say that please Ethan
warrant them the top of the pile for the
time being here's Xavier
Alana Garcia whose race is run I'm
afraid 12th place for him I'd like to
move up a spot or two if he can with
this in with three and a half
somersaults with tuck oh the wheels have
come off and they're bouncing down the
street now not to be caught
unfortunately a real shame that's three
poor ties from javi
yeah this is what happens sometimes you
lose it
diving is very much like that sometimes
when your head starting it over rotating
low to splash coming up yeah into the
hot tub and yeah I don't know where I am
we're doing what's going on and feeling
over the shop
tough day yeah and the marks won't make
you feel any better either appeared on
your screen bring up three point five
what he was hoping for with that the
total mark thirty five point seven zero
now Chris me is his fifth round I've got
two big ones to finish in with three and
a half somersaults tuck three point four
degree of difficulty he's just done the
same as hobby just before him overcooked
it just staying in his tuck shape a
little bit you could see on the
expression he knows instant feedback
when the water smacks you in the lower
back in the back of the legs all the
aerial work is very very good just
hanging on a little bit you can see him
tipping over there
it's another surfboard moment what a
shame for me is look at that right over
the diving board aerial work is
excellent
just waiting too long before let's go
and over he goes timber fifty six point
one zero is the mark which now will be
confirmed for you on screen five point
five coaster boards a slightly better
than it looks like he won't finish in
12th place alexander de Partie for four
and a half this is his big dive doesn't
normally do this one he's giving it a
good go and just unfortunately let it
roll over there's his mum and dad
they're here to support him he's going
for broke just seems shaking his head he
knows he's just let the dive go not seen
him do this on the springboard certainly
hasn't competed it here at these Olympic
Games just rolling over as he goes in
he's only gonna get six national 7s out
his day parties campaign for a medal
over unfortunately what a shame / and
absolutely incredible athlete well he
gave me the go I see athletes do that
holding back is an olympic file you've
got to go for broke because the
competition is so severe and so fierce
as is being proved today because in the
echo masha is not in the mix at all
anymore back two and a half sour shots
with pike for the man from ukraine he's
been lost but round dive ninth after
round four
oh it's tidy it is a low degree of
difficulty and game of tactics elect
introduces lowest degree of difficulty
now when everyone are bringing in their
their big dives out at the higher degree
of difficulties so it's probably seven
seven and a half maybe an eighth so
kibosh the middle of the pack I think in
a lovely slow-motion camera work isn't
it just bringing the dives to the viewer
sixty seven point five zero selection of
seven point five marks for a Leo Kovak
Patrick hosting three point five degree
of difficulty 8004 stepped down a bit
reversed three and a half for the
remaining German he comes out all guns
blazing on that one yeah I think it was
there's a bit more applause than that
that was superb just faltering slightly
on his previous round the inwards this
reverse absolutely spot-on
diving both springboard and platform
long long training hours for this young
man but he seems to be able to take it
all in his stride quite tall for a diver
that's his biggest the biggest dive
high-scoring dive so far well over 90
points I guess you guessed correctly he
comes confirmation that you're spot-on
ninety four point five zero
[Music]
Oh times they've aggrieved if cookie
gives us 94.5 zero now Troy doom a 3.5
yeah it's a reverse three and a half
foot once again top position for the
American and a tough position for him
fifth place boy didn't quite rip the
entry such a shame I thought that that
was going to be just what they could
prove critical this Troy slightly off
the pace he stayed with it stay with the
diving board didn't skip off he's done
all the hard work and she rolls over
doesn't quite keep the splash time it's
gonna get eight but he would have needed
well over 90 points to stay in
contention I think that will leave him
just a little bit off the pace yeah a
couple of points behind
Patrick housing could be the toy Jame
slips and drops one more position now
here is our current leader all the
pressure on the are Castillo who enter
can he keep this fantastic run going
it's an easy dive those gonna lose some
points here he will back two and a half
somersault 3.0 this has to be absolutely
spot-on yes the others will be catching
him after this well it's good but you
know this is the game of tactics yells
come out flexing his muscles doing all
his big dives early and absolutely
nailing them now this is his lowest
degree of difficulty and it's probably
its weakest his weakest dive so far just
arching into his back there it's only
gonna get eight he's gonna get what 72
73 75 at best with that back arch as he
goes in now the other boys are gonna go
and stick a 90 points plus on the board
and that's going to shake it up at the
standings well that's good enough to
keep it in the first place for now but
for the question is how much longer can
he you remain in pole position because
there's some big big dives coming up
including this one three point eight
were disastrously wrong for Ching Kai in
the prelims got it right in the semi as
though Ford four and a half somersaults
three
a word tuck this could be a hundred
points or more if he gets it right he's
just out a little bit early that is a
very very good dive it's an outstanding
takeoff he's up in the air completing
the dive almost effortless effortless
sleek sorry try and get my words out in
the excitement oh that's a shame I
thought it was gonna be the one he's out
a little early little short vertical as
he goes in it's gonna kill him well over
90 points as I mentioned that could
shake up the leaderboard or if you'd
waited in his shape just a fraction
longer we'd have seen him go over a
hundred points as it is it's ninety six
point nine zero point five work out the
scores with the lines through them as
ever do not and that puts him 25 points
clear of castillo welter but india
zakharov at some points oh that is
phenomenal you should stand up in the
crowd because we are witnessing
something truly extraordinary very hard
to please the russian coaches as you can
see but it's not very difficult to
please me that's going to go nearly 100
points it's three point nine a forward
two and a half with three twists you
other man my goodness means I come off
wow what do you know what it's not quite
the man ninety nine point four five the
gap between one and two is now one point
two five points Oh game on come on he
Chon what have you got in your toy box
Ching Kai and zakharov are separated by
one point two five points going into the
final round
and there's another Chinese you might
have ever say about the outcome of this
competition he is her song board four
and a half is he aiming for a hundred
points this time to shake it all up
oh yes - he needs a hundred points and
that is going to be very far away at all
and I can safely say I'm not
disappointed
look at that zakharov he's not even
bothered no point in looking at what you
can't control let them get on with it
all I can do is concentrate on my next
dive and her tongue is soaking up this
pressure easily completes a dive maybe
just a fraction over a vertical so or I
don't know where's he going to be dudes
have some points to make up so he's
certainly not going to be top of the
leaderboard fourth not in the medals yet
but he's one point behind the Middle's
Wow that's how tight this competition it
is unbelievably close for both one and
two and three and four just look at this
452 plays 451 for 27 plays for 26 that's
how it looks for the medals I think
that's where the medals are gonna go but
who's gonna get what after counting in
five troy Dumais in six we've got 3.9
coming at me
we talked you through the phone of mine
dives are those top four as you share
with us who's at the back yeah Chris
Meers
in 11th place still and they can you
know just above him in 10th no medals
today for warrant a party or cabassa so
the battle for the bonds between oh it
looks like the Battle of the bonds
between caste Leo and he Chong so you've
got a three point seven versus a three
point nine so it's pretty much die for
dive the interesting thing is Ching Kai
and Ilya Zakharov
Ching Kai only has a three point three
versus zakharov three point eight that
he scored a hundred points on in the
semi-finals or come on boy oh boy is
this a competition or is this a
competition it is as tight as a drum the
first and second and third and fourth
and we are loving it
these are these support players we'll
see first though in round number six the
final round or can you his last
competitive died before retirement is a
back two and a half sour sorts with Pike
3.0 degree of difficulty
thanks for all your contributions Kent I
want to dive to finish his career on
second Olympic Games getting fine
support there from his teammates did so
well to make this final and this what a
final to dive in as well
Wow and he gets to open it up he's the
first diver to complete all six dives
it's a fine job to finish and I'm sure
you're moved to coaching waving to the
crowd enjoying his time out here why
don't Kenny go 75 and goodbye Ken with
eight point five and eight certainly a
nice way to bow out eleven more to go
Ethan Warren for Australia he was a
battle well he's dived well for the most
part he's not gonna be featuring in the
medals now hi can he get up these
standings forward two and a half
somersaults to twist three point four
degree of difficulty to finish off for
the Australian and they'll perform this
in the pike position
oh what a terrific set of dives this
young man from Australia's performed
shouting and cheering from Matthew
Mitchum still to perform Olympic
champion himself appreciating his
teammates efforts here and he's done a
really really sterling performance great
job at the beginning in the field he's
going to get close to 500 points and
that is incredible
let's see what the final score is for
Ethan Warren it is four hundred eighty
eight point nine five eighty one point
600 fine all daimyo is I think other
competitions and may well have won it
all got a silver medal but the
competition so fierce and so intense
here eighty one point six and four
eighty eight point nine five not white
enough probably silver spoon is today
but he's come through a pack of twenty
nine to get into the twelve is Xavier
Garcia the applause from the crowd let
it die down before they reverse one and
a half somersaults three and a half
twists you won't have seen this by
anybody else I see relatively good died
for having to finish who did struggle on
his previous few rounds but as Bob was
saying great these here teammates from
years ago they're from the Spanish team
waving to the crowd East thank their
support this is old-school
one-and-a-half somersaults three and a
half twist so good dive to finish on for
Javy will take his learnings away still
got some life left in him I'm short will
see him back again and the mark which
the crowd of privy to you are now eighty
one point six zero for Xavier Alana
Garcia three eighths and that was him
dumb
now our final dive and he has acquitted
himself brilliantly over three rounds
and hasn't let anybody down and we'll be
back for more World Championships next
year Commonwealth Games in 2014 and the
next Olympics we hope his body holds
together for Rio Chris Meers this is his
big one to finish see it by other people
how will he do on the Ford four and a
half somersaults we took 3.8 top of the
shop for him I want to tie to finish on
us exactly what he did in the
semi-finals
there's his mom and dad and family they
should be oh so proud and I certainly am
too here in the comity brought such a
nice guy
water dive to finish on I thought after
the semifinals will he match it in the
final and he has saved the best until
last this is 3.8 he goes oh so high
cruising dipping into the water
marginally over a vertical beautiful rip
entry congratulating Ethan Warren there
these divers are all great mates as well
such a good sport coached by Lindsey
Fraser inside oh oh let's see what he
gets for the marks here they are 100.7
steady on Bobby Stephan me Oh better
than he went in the semi 591 in the semi
final 100 301 in the final goodness me
Christmas you have a future in this poor
boy if you didn't already know that
traumatic
extraordinary well done Chris
now probably young step when we say to
the old master a little bit still quite
youthful still has plenty to give to
Alex day party for two and a half with
two twists oh you gave him the
commentators curse he had exactly what
happened to Jack law yesterday in the
prelims the or the knee-trembler the
knee buckle I'll show you on the replay
he's gone to for the big one his knees
have just given out and the diving board
he's unbelievable that he managed to to
manage to complete the dive he will get
some marks on that Wow drama in this
last wine look his knees just give out
there nothing you could do about that
Oh wall away yeah he's worked so hard to
get here his head on the diving board
six weeks ago and that's not the way
that he wanted to end his Olympic
campaign here in London I don't think
there's anything really that we haven't
seen in this competition preliminaries
so many fine or or final it's been four
of unbelievable drama now we're into
that suspense about who's gonna get the
medals it won't be this man Elia kabocha
though he thought he had the pedigree to
do so to push for Italy's but hasn't
quite worked out for a forward two and a
half somersaults two twists three point
four in the pike position for its final
dive
there you go commercial showing you how
the guys should be done Tea Party
struggling buckling at the knees
commercia
staying with the diving board using it
rhythm wise here we go
up he goes one and a half some shots I
into the double twist turn into the pike
he's done a reasonable job today throws
knee kovash up three liam semies and
here in the final middle of the pack I
think in the end maybe just above me is
let's see the mark is eighty six point
seven yeah a six point seven confirmed
on the screen eight point five so he
does move above Chris Meers just behind
Ethan Warren as he won't wait Barney for
Warren in the m26 points fine the
australian sharp end of the competition
but probably not sharp enough for
patrick housing to get there this is big
this big it's 3.7 reverse two and a half
somersaults two and a half twists for
the German well how did he manage that
from the fulcrum end of the diving board
he's way back from the end of the diving
board and he has to do one of the most
complicated dives possible look he's way
back from the end yes to lean right over
the diving board oh and he still moves
it away a safe distance and manages to
drill the entry Wow I'm running out of
superlatives a truly terrific it's
astonishing how he managed to do that I
am I would give him extra points because
he was nowhere near the end of the
diving port three point seven is gonna
get over 90 points
it does 94.3 5 iPhone 5 total also to
find the laws of gravity yeah five oh
five point five five if you get over 500
you expect to get a medal normally and
he probably won't zone Troy do May
[Applause]
again enjoying the attention join me
crowd noise and it has been absolutely
fever pitch in here tonight last dive
three point four again forwards two and
a half several sorts two twists doom a
trying to get the top five finish I
finishes on his best IV always favors
this and that's as good as it gets for
Troy to mate just a little bit off the
pace not because of his dive just maybe
lacking a little bit of degree of
difficulty but he's going to go close to
500 Willie nip over it I'm not sure it's
going to be close but that is a
beautiful dive to finish the
all-important entry into the water
hardly a ripple of splash as he goes in
yep there's his mama dads they like it
and I certainly like it well done Troy
showing secretions to already want an
Olympic medal here just a little shy of
the 500 mile but early just 80 8.40
takes him to four ninety eight point
three five and for the time being its
second now how much pressure well that
was a little nervous look wasn't it
wasn't it just oh here you go much
pressure looking up and everything now
he is there on yellow Castillo Huerta at
the moment he is in bronze medal
position but there is no room for
maneuver and no room for error
this has to be absolutely spot-on from
medal you think reverse two-and-a-half
somersaults to an hour twist could he
pick up another Mexican middle
Oh No he has opened the door to none
other than he Chong
her Chong there he is he knows what he
needs to do his name is last Ivan and
medalists his Yale five out of five in
his last dive he's gone for the big one
this is reverse two and a half two and a
half twist he just skips off the diving
board a little bit aggressively there
leaving himself too much to do and he
lands on his shoulders now that's
throwing up a lot of splash he could get
taken out by hosting into Maine maybe
but I think he had enough buffer what an
absolute shame he's gone for broke he
has gone for broke he didn't use this in
the semis he went for it in a big way no
maybe it's gonna see him blow out or and
it does Oh
he's dropped down below housing and to
me Wow Oh No after so much good work
five pretty much impeccable rounds 86 85
95 8972 bit down on that a 64 Ching Kai
current leader he's got pressure on him
from zakharov so he has to get it right
everybody needs to be right on their
game now reverse two and a half I've a
three point three remember only three
points three but apart from that little
bit of splash it's absolutely brilliant
technically needed to be spot-on which
it was he landed on the end of the
diving boards no mistakes here on the
take-off one and a half twist fault into
that Pike shape and apart from this
little bit of splash that's a perfectly
vertical entry I don't think he's gonna
get much change out of nines maybe the
judges would go with him and give him
9.5 s and that puts the pressure firmly
on zakharov the only diver two divers to
go Ching Kai loves it shaking his fist
how much does he like it now it's the
judges like it eighty-nine point one
zero I make it the zakharov has to get
91 with his dive to overtake him in the
region of 91 now 541 I just written that
down just to make sure 541 now
what can this man do he needs
[Applause]
[Music]
19.4 90.4 required to win for Ilya
Zakharov it's a three point 82 this
perfectly this morning forward four and
a half summer sorts with tuck that's
gold for Russia that is definitely gold
for Russia China have not had it all the
wrong way look at the British team
jumping up there they are appreciative
of this super special Russian diver he
is the Olympic champion I can tell you
before the scores come up this is no no
that's unbelievable what a dive to
finish on probably coast to 100 points
like he did in the semi finals this
morning I take my hat off to you sucker
off you are the man you are the man
we're waiting for the mark of the
crowler waiting for the mark he's
waiting for the mark just confirmation
surely over Russian gold his time again
he's done it again
even better than before no perfect tense
will count sadly because that will have
put the tin lid on it and confirmed but
104 point five zero that is immense and
impeccable five five five point nine
zero that is in a completely different
stratosphere in this competition I
cannot believe what I've just seen there
zakharov stops the chinese gold rush
or does he yeah course it's possible for
her Chong to get anything better than
bronze but that is wide open for him now
wide open
Chong leads 80 really my calculations
are right he needs 80 so providing this
goes well three point nine degree of
difficulty that should take him
comfortably saving over that mark
yeah that'll get him because it's such a
big degree of difficulty he's been a
little bit off his game today
yeah no danger for you psycho off you
are the Olympic champion her Chong that
is good enough for bronze gold four
years ago long time four years this is
the polite for two and a half three
twist is a big degree of difficulty 3.9
her Chong will see himself on the podium
but not in the position he wanted to be
qualified top for this final ends up
being beaten by his country low country
munching CAI and truly outstanding Ilya
Zakharov the world champion is no longer
the Olympic champion 97.5 zero it is
good enough for third and no better for
her Chong and the old order has been
overturned China have won five golds
they're not going to win six in a row
because Ilya Zakharov has done it again
with the most immense sixth round dive
with a hundred and four point five zero
look at King Kai he's giving it his all
look at that 541 and that's not good
enough to win the gold look at this
elation and devastation the camera just
cut for one to the other someone
achieves her dream and another one loses
it all in the same instant welcome to
the Olympic Games let me just give me
the sequins and marks for Ilya Zakharov
eighty-five ninety one eighty nine point
two five eighty six point seven zero
ninety nine point four five one oh four
point five zero now perhaps he knows how
the rest of them feel because always
Chinese gold or seems to me anyway but
not this time round the world champion
is not the Olympic champion
amazing scenes here at the diving points
eating chi there in tears this is how
much it means to these athletes what a
treat for the spectators here to watch
that now let me just tell you 555 that
is unbelievable I have never seen diving
like that just 21 years old Ilya
Zakharov I don't think he's going
anywhere for a bit looks a little bit
like to meet you the great multi Olympic
gold winning medallist here his hero and
I'm not surprised he walks like he talks
like him and he certainly dives better
than him dare I say what an athlete and
what a contest well I don't think that
smiles going to come off his face for a
little while and all surely that is
amazing 21 years of age didn't even come
close to dropping a dive in that
sequence of six China have to settle and
be satisfied whether they're not of
course which you can tell by their
expressions with silver and two bronze
because that gold is returning to Russia
he can't quite believe it
the crowd are delighted to see something
a little bit different bat in the diving
pool and plenty of support that one I'm
Celia Cash's support group are now
adopting second off they can't get the
t-shirts made up that quickly
unfortunately
Ilya Zakharov is the winner five 55.90
it's just as amazing as I'm saying I
can't believe it Ching Kai her Chong one
two three patrick housing missing out by
one was twenty marks on the bronze troy
do mate
yeah castillo Huerta who threw it away
last dive through a chance of a medal
away and where did Chris Meers finish in
the end look he's made up to ninth place
with that terrific last dive that's
where he came in and that's where he
goes out in ninth place for thirty-nine
point seven five his day will come again
and it'd be much further up the pecking
order next time
right deep breath time everybody because
that is astonishing work we've kind of
been building up the Timmy's or is the
big climatic event of these Olympic
Games in diving but I tell you what the
10 is going to take some going to beat
that is it not well let's just wait and
see we have been treated to just contest
after contest if they're well the
highest performances and some well those
all sorts in that competition from start
to finish wasn't there so I you know the
platform is a blue-ribbon event the
women start tomorrow evening in the
polymer ease and then the men get to
close late on Saturday night local time
and I'm just taking each Drive at a time
in each contest at a time because it is
an absolute treat I've been involved in
this sport since you know I was eight
years old
and it just gets better and better and
better and I hope you enjoying it all
over the world because we certainly are
here we've got a best seat in the house
we've also got two microphones to bring
it alive so I hope you enjoyed it as
much as we are
does Ilya Zakharov have ice running
through his veins out they they are in a
situation you know that you got your
biggest dive to come you know if you do
it well you're a little bit gold
medalist but there's no sign of nerves
he bettered what he did the semi-final
we thought that was pretty exceptional
he's actually gone beyond that yeah well
that's what to true champions you know
become Olympic champion by not being
able to hold it together in the greatest
arena that there is you know this
gladiatorial out there there's
everyone's staring at you you're
standing there on the diving board all
those years and years and thousands and
thousands of dives in training come down
to this one moment in time one dive at a
time each of those six dives counts and
it's important that you nail all of them
so Yale castilho my heart goes out to
him because that final dive he went for
broke that was a big dive he upped the
ante Ted and even more complicated dive
that he did in the semi finals
they went for broke and unfortunately he
broke he didn't do it he didn't nail it
and he ended up outside the medals
whereas Ilya Zakharov from the start
opened up with his easiest
dive in his easiest dive is three point
four degree of difficulty that is
normally the most difficult dive he is a
cut above and what an amazing
performance and to do it here when it
counts in school
555 that is Wow
unbelievable can we be a little bit
parochial for a little while those
around the world I hope you won't mind
our self indulge us a bit only to die
was well over a hundred today one of
them was British yeah very good from
Chris you know he's got a lot of work to
do on his list and his consistency the
reverse turn off somersaults in the
second round led him down otherwise he'd
have been even higher up four thirty
nine he's a very very good score but
what he has shown his bursts of
brilliance and that was in the end of
the semi-final to secure his berth in
this final and then he finished up on a
real treat for the home crowd wasn't he
I can't believe how noisy it is in here
I think I get used to it and then I get
surprised every time a member of Team GB
stands on the diving board and I could
only begin to imagine what it might be
like as the week goes on fantastic
support in here people are loving their
diving's we're gaining all the love on
Twitter from around the world so thank
you for that and we'll continue to work
hard to bring it alive and explain some
of the nuances and idiosyncrasies of the
sport but the divers are doing all the
talking aren't they my goodness me we
don't have to do very much at all when
the diving is that good from the from
the home athletes as well as all of
these fantastic divers from all around
the world and you know let's go through
it again
that is the first gold that hasn't gone
to China in the 2012 Olympic Games in
the diving pool now that is quite
something everyone was you know
predicting a clean sweep and it's been
stopped on event number six actually I
think this is the one that most people
thought was the strongest the whole lot
wasn't it
yeah one of the strongest I you know I
wouldn't ever underestimate Sackhoff and
he split the Chinese last year in
Shanghai so I'd say they're probably
dominance is stronger in the women's
events than the men's I think the mint
is more open maybe you know dare I say
the closed event the blue ribbon event
the men's platform you know is the door
open the rest of the world believe and
you know if you can do it I can do it
just get mad-- to Chris Meers for a
moment before we move on to other things
for 61 in the semi 439 in a finally
actually dropped down by 22 but actually
finished in the same place so in terms
our position exactly the same will he be
a little bit disappointed he's not
better than what he didn't assent me
when when marks do tend to be a bit
higher in the final generally yeah of
course he made some mistakes the second
vandiver's I highlighted in our previous
conversation you know he was down on
that a few other slight errors but you
know his job was to make it to the final
and enjoy it and that's exactly what he
did he handled the occasion he handled
himself you know superbly
under the pressure under the expectation
he smiled he enjoyed it and he let his
diving do the talking he's only 19 years
old he's got a lot of years ahead of him
I want a fantastic first Olympic
experience fifth in the synchronized
springboard event and then he's come out
and nailed it ninth in this individual
Wow I take my hat off very good indeed
why don't Chris me is how you feeling
for your good mate your very close
friend Alex day party didn't quite
finish or go out the way he wanted to a
tough day at the office for Alex you
know and he's had a really tough four
years
injury after injury after injury never
really seemed to get back into his
rhythm and really start to shine after
his silver medal in Beijing and that's
sometimes what happens he's been the top
of his game since he was 13 years old
way back in 1998 and here today you know
just goes to show it could happen to
anyone his last round dive instead of
getting 82 Plus which is what we
normally expect maybe even in the 90s
when he's on his game he got 22 points
and he's very fortunate to get that at a
complete knee buckle and we saw what
happens yesterday in the preliminaries
Jack Lord had completely buckle and
didn't even manage his dive completely
failed the dive and we saw Stefan feck
who slipped off the diving board so you
know it happens to everyone including
Olympic silver medalist from the
previous two games Alexandre de Partie
and of course my heart goes out to him
what a truly extraordinary athlete maybe
he'll you know retire after this it's
you know I'm sure that's his decision
and his announcement to make
and I certainly want to be speaking for
him I know that he would have wanted to
go out on a high so let's wait and see
see how he feels see what options he's
got
but he's you know world champion Olympic
silver medalist he's got absolutely
everything on his multiple Commonwealth
medalist he's got everything under his
belt one of the world's greatest divers
ever let's talk about the young guns
we've mentioned Chris Meers what about
Ethan Warren I think he's impressed you
press here the Commonwealth Games name
is pretty consistent again tonight yeah
absolutely he's just got better and
better he's turned up the ante you know
turned it up each time so prelims he was
in the mix semi finals he moved up
further into the mix and then final what
did he end up with 488 it's a big score
I mean it's it's shadowed by the where
would he come 7th yeah the top six will
ride out there 488 you know you'd expect
to be closer to the medals with that but
well not today not in the London Olympic
final for divers over 500 have we ever
seen that before
well not in Olympic Games for sure maybe
in a in a Grand Prix around the world
when the judging is more elevated you
might see that's why we can't have World
Records in diving because the judging
scores vary it depends you know how much
of a how much guidance they're giving
out the facts sometimes the the
powers-that-be would say okay judges you
need to be really strict on this
particular element of the dive so if you
see anyone with a split tuck shape
that's a tuck shape with their knees
wide apart make sure you penalize them
and you know it depends and that can
really influence the marks I think the
judging here has been very consistent
though Bob normally we have a bit more
of a rant about the judging but I think
here well have knowed you rant once
actually but we did maybe once or twice
you've had one but I've certainly been
very comfortable with the judging you
know there's you know the measures were
in place they take away the two highest
and the two lowest to leave the three
middle scores trying to advocate out all
the time in the synchro even more
complex but the intention is to try and
give to take away that subjectivity as
much as they can and try and averaged
out the scores before it is of course
multiplied by the degree of difficulty
and boy oh boy did we see some degrees
of difficulty here and all this week and
more to come of course with the with the
platform events to finish off this
extraordinary Olympic Games are we gonna
see four I was three point nine as far
as it's gonna go well they're you know
they're mathematically calculate a ball
if there's that's a made-up word they're
you know
yeah you can look at it it's almost like
a computer game if you can fit the spins
in there's a degree of difficulty which
will go next to it but at the moment 3.9
that's pushing the ceiling as far as I'm
concerned well we've been living off the
ceiling and on the ceiling during the
course of the evening and they were just
about to come down to Terra Firma after
what we've just seen I guess yeah you
got it right if you just tuned in in the
center of your screen is not a Chinese
diver yes to your left and to your right
but position that number one is occupied
by a Russian and how often do we see
this when the presentation part is
obviously agreed in advance this happens
all the time
they suspect it'll be a Chinese gold and
it's not a Russian who's could present
it
the Chinese presentation party
redick weird also some assistance from
Margot Mountjoy executive board member
of the governing body for water sports
around the world swimming diving water
polo open water and synchronized
swimming which is also taking place in
this very poor
that's the presentation party it seems
to me that India zakharov cannot wait to
stand up flat for me sir
jumpy around like a hyperactive kid I'm
sure you see much of a smile from her
Chong the world champion and Olympic
champion from Beijing muster a smile
because bronze is not what he came here
for and he was a fool there's somebody
sitting right you only get five hundred
and twenty four point one five points
who said yeah that's fine I'll take that
cuz that's gonna be a gold medal not on
this occasion it wasn't any good enough
for bronze if fatty was seventeen point
shy of silver and 31 points away from
gold it wasn't close just about
mustering a smile or regret their smile
really from her Chong his bronze for
China and it was silver for China here's
somebody who missed out on the medal
last year the World Championships in
fourth place he's gone to better this
time Ching Kai of China know he's
punching in the air think he's a bit
more happy with that than her charm
maybe thought he's gonna be a sole
medalist anyway didn't expect it to be a
Russian who beat him to the first place
yeah nice big a smile from the top
ranked Chinese this time
I think there might be a bit of a raw in
this building when the gold medalist is
announced so are people to stay behind
for the metal ceremony to acclaim well
not totally unexpected gold medalists he
was the silver medalist at the World
Championships in Shanghai last year but
he has gone one better with five hundred
and fifty five point nine zero points
astonishing and remarkable Ilya Zakharov
of Russia 21 years of age is the Olympic
men's 3-meter springboard champion big
gold medal goes around his neck it's
alighted to take the acclaim of the
crowd he will be a powerhouse and a
force to be reckoned with as long as the
body holds together for the next few
years he will be pushing and the Chinese
as he pushed them out the way today
India zakharov breaks the stranglehold
of the Chinese in diving events at
London 2012 and we will hear for the
first time the Russian national anthem
[Music]
remember that face remember the name
India zakharov the man who ended Chinese
domination in the men's 3-meter
springboard final with astonishing one
hundred and four point five zero eyes
final dive an overall total of five
hundred and fifty five point nine zero
we think it was close fourteen points
virtually separating first and second so
he did it his way he did the hard way
and he did it with that spectacular
final dive he'll have him immortalized
in Russian diving history last word for
you Leon well I don't know whether I've
got any words to add to that where can
we go from here you know we've got the
women's platform and the men's platform
still to go same process prelims in the
evening semi finals the next morning and
then the final in the evening so check
the timings check where you're gonna be
because if the diving continues at this
kind of standard which I'm pretty
confident it will Wow good words to
describe them yep we've gone from the
three we'll go to the ten for the
women's and the men's at the weekend we
are looking forward to that so much I
hope that the ever-growing band of
diving aficionados and Watchers will be
with us for the women's and of course
the men's to round off the program at
the weekend thank you for being with us
here at the Aquatic Centre at the heart
of London's Olympic Park it's been a
tremendous night particularly tremendous
night for Russia and Russian diving what
will happen in the women's ten meter
you'll find out with us in about 24
hours less from now from Leon Taylor
myself Bob Bala thank you for joining us
enjoy the rest of your day
you
[Music]